Preliminary Inventory to the Walter L. Leschander Collection, 1938-1965
Hoover Institution Archives
Walter L. Leschander Collection,
1938-1965
66023
Leschander, Walter L., collector.
9 manuscript boxes. (3.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, diary, correspondence, photographs, maps, clippings, and pamphlets, relating to espionage, military intelligence, prisoners of war, and escape techniques, primarily during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Best, Sigismung Payne.; Blum, Léon, 1872-1950.; Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945.; Espionage.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Netherlands.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.; Germany.; Great Britain.; Netherlands.; Netherlands--History--German occupation, 1940-1945.
Container List
- Venlo Incident (Box 1.)
  - 1. Dutch Government inquiry into the Venlo incident. Translations made by Captain Best, his comments added in red. Index
  - 1a. Mate to globe which held 1st atom bomb and kick-off switch for boosters on planes from Doolittle's raid on Tokyo
  - 2. Original manuscript of Captain Payne Best: The Venlo Incident (2 parts) (Box 2.)
  - 3. Annotated and inscribed copy of book The Venlo Incident
  - 4. Payne Best's prison diary, 1938-1942
  - 5. Walter L. Leschander's research notes on Venlo incident and Captain Best's answers to his questions
  - 6. Scrapbook "General van Oorschot." Correspondence between Best and Oorschot on events preceding the Venlo incident, the assignment of a Dutch officer to Best and Stevens, Oorschot's testimony before the Dutch Commission of Inquiry, letters of Prince Bernhard of the Netherlands to Best, 1948 (Box 3.)
  - 7. Scrapbook "Lt. Col. R. H. Stevens." Postwar correspondence between Best and Stevens. Also included are originals of prison letters sent by Stevens to Best, on tiny sheets of paper or cardboard, copies transcribed on typewriter
  - 8. Scrapbook "Venlo Holland." Newspaper clippings, photographs, correspondence dealing with the Venlo incident, including pictures of Best
  - 9. Postwar newspaper clipping on Captain Best and review of the book The Venlo Incident
- Colditz Castle prison (Box 4.)
  - 10. Scrapbook "Colditz Castle," containing photographs (identified,) some correspondence, some follow-ups on survivors of Colditz including a man living in Watts, Los Angeles, whose store was burned in the August 1964 riots
  - 11. File of correspondence and manuscripts: Leschander-Dr. Reinhold Eggers, author of story on Colditz prison
  - 12. Colditz file; escape story of Lt. J. E. R. Wood as told to Leschander
- Payne Best (Box 5.)
  - 13. Tape transcriptions. Best's memoirs, occasionally going back to World War I
  - 14. Clippings and duplicates of tape transcriptions
  - 15. Four rolls of tape - Miscellaneous material (including Best's authorization to use material)
  - 16. Leschander-Clayton Hutton escape devices (gadgets) (Box 6.)
  - 17. Leschander-Halder correspondence, 1962-1965
  - 18. Manuscripts by Walter Leschander: "A Chicken Saved Verdun; "Hitler's Fake Bomb Plot; "What Price Treason"; untitled manuscript detailing Leschander's researches
  - 19. Miscellaneous correspondence, 1959-1966
- Miscellany (Box 7.)
  - 20. Lecture given in January 1951 by Captain Payne Best "The Other Man" manuscript
  - 21. Legal proceedings, 1951, against concentration camp guard Edgar Stiller. Best, who knew him, tried to interest survivors of the last days of the camp, including Franz Halder, to give testimony in favor of Stiller
  - 22. Story "I Was Hanged by the Nazis" by Ronald Seth (various manuscript versions)
  - 23. Essay by Erich Gimpel, a World War II German spy caught in the United States
  - 24. Pess clippings on Gordon Lonsdale case, 1961
  - 25. Liberation in the South Tyrolese Dolomites
  - 26. Payne Best - Léon Blum correspondence, 1945-1947
  - 27. Scrapbook, "Germany East-West Frontier, 1963 (contains mounted photographs, identified)
  - 28. Accession books for Leschander book collection, nos. 1 and 2
- Additional material (Box 8.)
  - 1. Maps (large scale) of Germany issued by the British War Office and U.S. Army Map Service, 1944, and revisions
  - 2. Photographs (official U.S. Army photos) of marines in China, Tarawa, Pearl Harbor, Atomic bomb, Japanese surrender, German atrocities
  - 3. Royal Air Force Escaping Society, (2 pamphlets)
  - 4. Siege of Tobruk, 1941 April-December - cartography and history, (1 map, annotated)
  - 5. Photographic reproductions of the Zeppelin L49 that was forced to land... by French aviators, 1917 October 20, (1 envelope)
- Letters and comments to and from Captain Sigismund Payne Best of a confidential nature pertaining to the people and events surrounding the Venlo Incident (Box 9.)